<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>About on Alexandra Edwards, PhD</title>
    <link>http://nonmodernist.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in About on Alexandra Edwards, PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="http://nonmodernist.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/intro/</guid>
      <description>Introduction: Women, Cinema, Nation # As a woman, I have no country. As a woman, I want no country. As a woman, my country is the whole world.
&amp;ndash;Virginia Woolf
Since our class meets once a week, we are diving right in on the first day with an introduction to the course and a discussion of the three terms we are going to keep in mind during the semester: women, cinema, nation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading List</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/anarchist-nonfiction-across-genres/collapsed/reading-list/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/anarchist-nonfiction-across-genres/collapsed/reading-list/</guid>
      <description>Reading List # Intro to Anarchism # Kim Kelly, &amp;ldquo;Anarchy&amp;rdquo; David Graeber, &amp;ldquo;Are You an Anarchist? The Answer May Surprise You&amp;rdquo; Precursors to Anarchism # Etienne de la Boetie, Discourse on Voluntary Servitude (excerpt), 1549 The Diggers, &amp;ldquo;The True Levellers Standard Advanced&amp;rdquo;, 1649 William Godwin, An Enquiry Concerning Political Justice (excerpt),	1793 Christian Anarchism # Adin Ballou, &amp;ldquo;Non-Resistant Catechism&amp;rdquo;,	1844 Leo Tolstoy, &amp;ldquo;Evil Cannot Be Suppressed by the Physical Form of the Government&amp;rdquo; from The Kingdom of God Is Within You, 1894 Anarchism&amp;rsquo;s Rhetorical Questions # Pierre-Joseph Proudhon, What is Property?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statement of Goals</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/anarchist-nonfiction-across-genres/collapsed/statement-of-goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/anarchist-nonfiction-across-genres/collapsed/statement-of-goals/</guid>
      <description>Statement of Goals # Let us rethink discipline. One of the worst things about the arbitrary form of authority we see in the classroom is the way it makes us lose our trust in the possibility of learning from people who know what they’re doing and could share their wisdom with us. When they make you obey a cruel and unreasonable teacher, they can curtail your desire to learn from a kind and reasonable wise person.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Male Gaze</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/male-gaze/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/male-gaze/</guid>
      <description>The Male Gaze # In a world ordered by sexual imbalance, pleasure in looking has been split between active/male and passive/female. The determining male gaze projects its fantasy onto the female figure, which is styled accordingly. In their traditional exhibitionist role women are simultaneously looked at and displayed, with their appearance coded for strong visual and erotic impact so that they can be said to connote to-be-looked-at-ness.
&amp;ndash;Laura Mulvey, &amp;ldquo;Visual Pleasure and Narrative Cinema&amp;rdquo;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Panopticon</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/panopticon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/panopticon/</guid>
      <description>The Panopticon # Visibility is a trap. &amp;ndash;Michel Foucault, Discipline and Punish
At the same time that John Berger and Laura Mulvey were exploring the male gaze, French philosopher Michel Foucault was writing about a different, yet related, type of looking: surveillance. Researching historical penal systems led Foucault to argue that the shift from public executions to imprisonment represented a new and different relationship between people and power&amp;ndash;especially the power of institutions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collaborative Film Zine</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/zine/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/zine/</guid>
      <description>Collaborative Film Zine # Read the Zine! # Women, Cinema, Nation film zine, shared with permission of the contributors.
Instructions # In the final weeks of the course, we will plan and create a collaborative zine that showcases your creative and analytical work on a topic we&amp;rsquo;ve examined. This zine will serve as a record of our semester, a celebration of our intellectual community, and a chance for you each to dive deeper into a theoretical concept or film that speaks to you.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collaborative Mutual Aid Project Proposal</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/anarchist-nonfiction-across-genres/collapsed/collaborative-mutual-aid-project-proposal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/anarchist-nonfiction-across-genres/collapsed/collaborative-mutual-aid-project-proposal/</guid>
      <description>Collaborative Mutual Aid Project Proposal # “A critique of the charity model is that it’s designed to keep poor people poor and dependent on wealthy benefactors who get to feel good about themselves. Mutual aid, in contrast, is about the collective redistribution of resources and creating interdependence. The practice of people having one another’s backs when they’ve been cut off from formal avenues of support has been a way of life for Black, Indigenous, brown, and immigrant communities in the U.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Midterm Self-Assessment</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/anarchist-nonfiction-across-genres/collapsed/midterm-self-assessment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/anarchist-nonfiction-across-genres/collapsed/midterm-self-assessment/</guid>
      <description>Midterm Self-Assessment # Instructions # This written exam is comprised of 4 essay questions: 2 are required and 2 may be chosen from the short lists below. Each answer should directly reference materials we have read for Weeks 1-6 of class. The exam is open-note, open-book, open-internet—but plagiarism of another’s work or words is a violation of the academic conduct policy.
Genre (this question is required; minimum 300 words) # Choose 2 texts we read that represent different genres.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Penetrating Looks</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/penetrating-looks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/penetrating-looks/</guid>
      <description>Penetrating Looks # When the Final Girl (in films like Hell Night, Texas Chainsaw II, and even Splatter University) assumes the &amp;lsquo;active investigating gaze&amp;rsquo;, she exactly reverses the look, making a spectacle of the killer and a spectator of herself.
&amp;ndash;Carol Clover, Men, Women, and Chainsaws
Slasher films present us in startlingly direct terms with a world in which male and female are at desperate odds but in which, at the same time, masculinity and femininity are more states of mind than body.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disciplinary Gender</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/disciplinary-gender/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/disciplinary-gender/</guid>
      <description>Discinplinary Gender # For the most part, feminist theory has assumed that there is some existing identity, understood through the category of women, who not only initiates feminist interests and goals within discourse, but constitutes the subject for whom political representation is pursued.
&amp;ndash;Judith Butler, Gender Trouble
Gender is not always constituted coherently or consistently in different historical contexts&amp;hellip; gender intersects with racial, class, ethnic, sexual, and regional modalities of discursively constituted identities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Final Self-Assessment</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/anarchist-nonfiction-across-genres/collapsed/final-self-assessment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/anarchist-nonfiction-across-genres/collapsed/final-self-assessment/</guid>
      <description>Final Self-Assessment # Instructions # This written exam is comprised of 5 essay questions: 3 are required and 2 may be chosen from the short lists below. Please note that the self-assessment question is in three parts; all three parts must be answered. Every answer should directly reference materials we have read, watched, and listened to during the semester. The exam is open-note, open-book, open-internet—but plagiarism of another’s work or words is a violation of the academic conduct policy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Imperial Leather</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/imperial-leather/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/imperial-leather/</guid>
      <description>Imperial Leather # The feminizing of terra incognito was, from the outset, a strategy of violent containment&amp;ndash;belonging in the realm of both psychoanalysis and political economy.
&amp;ndash;Anne McClintock, Imperial Leather
Knowledge of the unknown world was mapped as a metaphysics of gender violence&amp;ndash;not as the expanded recognition of cultural difference&amp;ndash;and was validated by the new Enlightenment logic of private property and possessive individualism.
&amp;ndash;Anne McClintock, Imperial Leather
In previous entries, I have marked certain words in bold font to suggest that they are important concepts for us to track.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PIcturing Colonial Violence</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/colonial-violence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/colonial-violence/</guid>
      <description>Picturing Colonial Violence # African women must be everywhere. They must be in the images, behind the camera, in the editing room and involved in every stage of the making of a film. They must be the ones to talk about their problems.
&amp;ndash;Sarah Maldoror
Imagine a conversation between Frantz Fanon and Sarah Maldoror about colonial violence. What might they agree on? What might they disagree on?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
