<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Film and Reading List on Alexandra Edwards, PhD</title>
    <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Film and Reading List on Alexandra Edwards, PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/intro/</guid>
      <description>Introduction: Women, Cinema, Nation # As a woman, I have no country. As a woman, I want no country. As a woman, my country is the whole world.
&amp;ndash;Virginia Woolf
Since our class meets once a week, we are diving right in on the first day with an introduction to the course and a discussion of the three terms we are going to keep in mind during the semester: women, cinema, nation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Male Gaze</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/male-gaze/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/male-gaze/</guid>
      <description>The Male Gaze # In a world ordered by sexual imbalance, pleasure in looking has been split between active/male and passive/female. The determining male gaze projects its fantasy onto the female figure, which is styled accordingly. In their traditional exhibitionist role women are simultaneously looked at and displayed, with their appearance coded for strong visual and erotic impact so that they can be said to connote to-be-looked-at-ness.
&amp;ndash;Laura Mulvey, &amp;ldquo;Visual Pleasure and Narrative Cinema&amp;rdquo;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Panopticon</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/panopticon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/panopticon/</guid>
      <description>The Panopticon # Visibility is a trap. &amp;ndash;Michel Foucault, Discipline and Punish
At the same time that John Berger and Laura Mulvey were exploring the male gaze, French philosopher Michel Foucault was writing about a different, yet related, type of looking: surveillance. Researching historical penal systems led Foucault to argue that the shift from public executions to imprisonment represented a new and different relationship between people and power&amp;ndash;especially the power of institutions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Penetrating Looks</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/penetrating-looks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/penetrating-looks/</guid>
      <description>Penetrating Looks # When the Final Girl (in films like Hell Night, Texas Chainsaw II, and even Splatter University) assumes the &amp;lsquo;active investigating gaze&amp;rsquo;, she exactly reverses the look, making a spectacle of the killer and a spectator of herself.
&amp;ndash;Carol Clover, Men, Women, and Chainsaws
Slasher films present us in startlingly direct terms with a world in which male and female are at desperate odds but in which, at the same time, masculinity and femininity are more states of mind than body.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disciplinary Gender</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/disciplinary-gender/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/disciplinary-gender/</guid>
      <description>Discinplinary Gender # For the most part, feminist theory has assumed that there is some existing identity, understood through the category of women, who not only initiates feminist interests and goals within discourse, but constitutes the subject for whom political representation is pursued.
&amp;ndash;Judith Butler, Gender Trouble
Gender is not always constituted coherently or consistently in different historical contexts&amp;hellip; gender intersects with racial, class, ethnic, sexual, and regional modalities of discursively constituted identities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Imperial Leather</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/imperial-leather/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/imperial-leather/</guid>
      <description>Imperial Leather # The feminizing of terra incognito was, from the outset, a strategy of violent containment&amp;ndash;belonging in the realm of both psychoanalysis and political economy.
&amp;ndash;Anne McClintock, Imperial Leather
Knowledge of the unknown world was mapped as a metaphysics of gender violence&amp;ndash;not as the expanded recognition of cultural difference&amp;ndash;and was validated by the new Enlightenment logic of private property and possessive individualism.
&amp;ndash;Anne McClintock, Imperial Leather
In previous entries, I have marked certain words in bold font to suggest that they are important concepts for us to track.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Picturing Colonial Violence</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/colonial-violence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/colonial-violence/</guid>
      <description>Picturing Colonial Violence # African women must be everywhere. They must be in the images, behind the camera, in the editing room and involved in every stage of the making of a film. They must be the ones to talk about their problems.
&amp;ndash;Sarah Maldoror
Imagine a conversation between Frantz Fanon and Sarah Maldoror about colonial violence. What might they agree on? What might they disagree on?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Veil</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/veil/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/veil/</guid>
      <description>The Veil # Compare any woman character in Sambizanga to any woman character in The Day I Became a Woman. How do these depictions demonstrate Chandra Talpade Mohanty&amp;rsquo;s argument that &amp;ldquo;third world women&amp;rdquo; are not a monolithic category?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Oppositional Gaze</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/oppositional-gaze/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/oppositional-gaze/</guid>
      <description> The Oppositional Gaze # In our reading for this week, So Mayer asserts, &amp;ldquo;What queer feminists do onscreen—and to the screen—is theory.&amp;rdquo;
In what ways does The Watermelon Woman &amp;ldquo;do theory&amp;rdquo;? In particular, how does Cheryl Dunye use the film to theorize what bell hooks calls &amp;ldquo;the oppositional gaze&amp;rdquo;?
Zine contribution by Avrie # </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Queer Lewks</title>
      <link>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/queer-lewks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://nonmodernist.com/docs/courses/theories-of-cinema/content/queer-lewks/</guid>
      <description> Queer Lewks # Paris is Burning is the only documentary we are watching this semester, although The Watermelon Woman used elements of documentary filmmaking in its fictional metanarrative.
Theorize why documentary might be a genre that appeals to queer storytellers telling queer stories. You should refer to either of this week&amp;rsquo;s readings in your response.
Zine contribution by Hayley # </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
